Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, so today's דף daf is דף ל"ג,
Daf Lamed Gimmel, סנהדרין Sanhedrin 33. We pick up at the second
line. We are just at the beginning of דיני ממונות, Dinei Mamonos,
looking at the differences between דיני נפשות Dinei Nefashos and דיני נפשות,
Dinei Nefashos, דיני נפשות Dinei Nefashos and דיני ממונות, Dinei Mamonos, and
we've seen now a difference between how you open the case, whereas
in דיני ממונות, Dinei Mamonos, you can open it בין לזכות בין
לחובה, bein lizchus bein lichova, whether to find the person exempt or
obligated. In דיני נפשות, Dinei Nefashos, you always open it first לזכות,
lizchus, trying to argue for the person's innocence and in his defense,
frame the issue that way, call for additional evidence as we saw
yesterday. Okay, and now we talk about whether you can call back
the case and reverse it. And the משנה Mishna said that דיני
ממונות Dinei Mamonos you can reverse whether to find somebody liable who
you had find exempt or reverse or find somebody exempt who you
had found liable. But in capital crimes, there's no double jeopardy. If
somebody is found innocent it cannot be reversed. However, if somebody is
found guilty, it can be reversed. It's sort of like appeal for
a guilty verdict, but no double jeopardy. So now let's take a
look at that. דיני ממונות מחזירין. Dinei Mamonos machzirin. ורמינהו, Urmini, he
says the גמרא, Gemara, second line from the top on ל"ג. Lamed
Gimmel. We taught and with this we came also much earlier in
the first פרק. perek. דן את הדין זיכה את החייב חייב את
הזכאי טימא את הטהור טיהר את הטמא. Dan es hadin zika es
hachayav chiyav es hazakai tima es hatahor tahar es hatamei. If somebody
rendered a judgment and they made a mistake, they found somebody liable
they found them to be exempt or somebody who was exempt they
found them to be liable or they made something impure pure, they
declared something to be pure that was impure.
So מה שעשה עשה, ma she'asa asa, what is done is done,
and the judge has to ישלם מביתו, yshalem mibeiso, has to pay
damages. So this is a fascinating case of, and we've seen this
of course, we saw this yesterday, we've seen this for a while,
the sense that there could be a liability for rendering a wrong
judgment. It's interesting as to who gets to decide that it was
a wrong judgment. But in addition to the issue about liability, and
if you as a judge caused something that was irreversible then you're
liable, and that has to do
with whole questions about why you're liable, is it you weren't מזיק
בידיים, mazik biyadyim, it's a type of a גרמא, grama, indirectly you
caused the loss of money, maybe it's an היזק דגרמי. hezek de'garmi.
But whatever that is, that's like a בבא קמא Bava Kamma question
about if you caused damage but you didn't directly perpetrate the damage
that you're liable. Is the, and that's one issue. The other issue
is who determines that you made the mistake. But the third issue,
which is immediately relevant for us, is that מה שעשה עשה, ma
she'asa asa, that the case is not reversible. Okay,
so our משנה Mishna however says that when a mistake is discovered
you can reverse a case in דיני ממונות. Dinei Mamonos. So how
do you reconcile this? אמר רב יוסף לא קשיא כאן במומחה כאן
בשאינו מומחה. Amar Rav Yosef lo kashya kan bemumcheh kan beshe'eino mumcheh.
The difference is if you're an expert or you're not an expert.
Now there's a whole question here about which way that goes and
what the גרסא girsah is. We're going to read it the way
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י's Rashi interpretation and רש"י's Rashi גרסא. girsah. And רש"י
Rashi says if you're a מומחה mumcheh you're able to reverse it,
if you're not a מומחה mumcheh you're not able to reverse it.
What's the logic behind that? So you know רש"י Rashi throughout this
explains that the reason you can't reverse it is because this is
a case that has two litigants and any reversal is going to
help one person and hurt the other. So the person that your
reversal is now going to hurt, let's say you found ראובן Reuven
liable and שמעון Shimon exempt. You know ראובן Reuven owes שמעון Shimon
a hundred dollars. And now you're going to reverse it and you're
going to say no I made a mistake, ראובן Reuven actually doesn't
owe the money. So שמעון Shimon is going to say why should
I trust your reversal now? You know if you're admitting you made
a mistake maybe now is the time you made a mistake, and
maybe in the first court case when you found me innocent, excuse
me, when you found ראובן Reuven owed me the money, that was
when you were right and now that you're trying to reverse it
now is the time you're wrong. I mean you're wrong one of
the times, why should I believe you that you're wrong now? So
because there's two litigants and one of them is always arguing to
keep the case the way it was initially ruled, you don't have
the power to reverse it. That's why מה שעשה עשה. ma she'asa
asa. But because you're admitting that you made a mistake, right, then
you have to pay the person who now you're saying that you
injured in your incorrect first ruling. That's the way רש"י Rashi explains
it. So therefore that idea that somebody can say I don't trust
you and how can you, on what basis are you saying that
now you've made the mistake and that before you made the mistake
and now you're right, I'm going to claim it's the reverse. So
if this person is a מומחה, mumcheh, okay, then he can say
that you know
that this guy is an expert and he can as an expert,
it's not like oh you don't know what you're doing and therefore
I can't trust you at all, because you're an expert and you
do know what you're doing I will trust your, you know, your
later judgment has weight and... and authority and therefore it can actually
be accepted and override your earlier judgment. Okay, if you take a
look at רש״י Rashi במומחה, bemumche, רש״י Rashi says three lines from
the top. יש בו כח לחזור ולא מצי למימר ליה אבדין אנא
כטעמא קמא דידך עבדינא. yesh bo koach lachzor velo matzi lemimar leh
avdin ana ketaama kama didach avdina. No, I'm going like your first,
you know, your first judgment, I'm saying you're making a mistake now.
If you're a מומחה, mumche, you have authority and your second considered
opinion can be weightier. אבל בשאינו מומחה מצי אמר ליה מי יימר
דטעמא בתרא דידך עיקר דילמא קמא עיקר ובהאי הוא דטעיתא. aval besheino
mumche matzi amar leh mi yeymar detaama batra didach ikkar dilma kama
ikkar uvehai hu detaita. Okay? So that's exactly as we said. If
you're, if you're not an expert, you say you don't know what
you're doing. And therefore I don't trust your later judgment any more
than your earlier. But if you are a מומחה mumche and you
have authority then you're able to override. Okay, so that's answer number
one. כאן במומחה כאן בשאינו מומחה. kan bemumche kan besheino mumche. ובמומחה
מחזירין. uvemumche machzirin. So the גמרא Gemara says is this really true
that if you're an expert then your second decision can be seen
as authoritative and override? והקתני היה מומחה לבית דין פטור מלשלם. vehakatani
haya mumche leveit din patur melashalem. But that very teaching that said
that, you know, what's done is done but you're liable, says but
if you were a מומחה mumche
then you're פטור. patur. So it sounds like what it's saying is
even if you're a מומחה mumche what's done is done but you
don't have to pay liability because if you're not an expert then
we just say it's because you're being negligent and irresponsible and you
have to pay liability. If you're an expert then okay, accidents happen.
But it's not due to negligence, it's not due to fault, and
you don't pay liability. That presumably is the difference. But it sounds
like in both cases what's done is done and the only question
is is there liability? אמר רב נחמן כאן שיש גדול הימנו בחכמה
ובמניין כאן שאין גדול הימנו בחכמה ובמניין. amar Rav Nachman kan sheyesh
gadol heimenu bechochmah uvevinyan kan she-ein gadol heimenu bechochmah uvevinyan. In one
case there is somebody of greater authority. It's interesting the phrase מניין.
minyan. מניין minyan like normally means like what's number. I mean that's
also true when it says about a בית דין beit din that's
גדול בחכמה ובמניין. gadol bechochmah uvevinyan. If every בית דין beit din
major בית דין beit din is the same size of seventy-one, what's
one that's bigger in number? So some say it means number of
תלמידים, talmidim, some say it means how old you are. It's a
strange phrase. Anyway, in one case it's a case of a מומחה
mumche with a higher authority and the other is one without a
higher authority. So the way רש״י Rashi explains it is is that
if you're a מומחה mumche but nobody is a greater authority than
you that can back up your reversal, so then you can't reverse
it. You know, again, maybe now's the mistake and before wasn't the
mistake, so you can't reverse it. How do you know one time,
you know, what makes your second decision better than your first even
for a מומחה? mumche? Although we for a מומחה mumche we do
say that if there was a mistake it was due to—no, there
was no liability and you're פטור מלשלם. patur melashalem. What is the
case that it can be reversed? When not only is this מומחה
mumche saying I made a mistake and there's reason we should believe
him, but that there's somebody of even greater authority that is saying
yes, your later decision is the correct one. Okay, so it's not
exactly like an appeals court. The מומחה mumche himself reverses, but because
he has somebody of greater authority to back him up, that allows
it to be overridden. So now what we're saying is a מומחה
mumche because if something will happen it's a total freak case, there's
no liability. When can it be reversed though? So either a—so that's
only a מומחה mumche who's backed up by somebody who's even higher
than he is.
Okay, that's basically version of answer number one. רב ששת אמר כאן
שטעה בדבר משנה כאן שטעה בשיקול הדעת. Rav Sheshet amar kan shetaah
bidvar mishnah kan shetaah beshikul hadaat. No,
it's not the difference between מומחה mumche or not מומחה. mumche. It's
the difference between is it a mistake of דבר משנה, dvar mishnah,
something that is like black-letter law? We'll discuss in a minute what
דבר משנה dvar mishnah means. It doesn't just mean something that appears
in a משנה. mishnah. A, because it includes also rulings later, and
B, not everything that appears in a משנה mishnah is הלכה. halacha.
But it basically means did they make a mistake in black-letter law,
something that is absolutely unquestionably the case, and it was so clearly
a complete mistake? Or was it a mistake in recent judgment, שיקול
הדעת? shikul hadaat? Was it a judgment mistake? All right, if it's
a mistake in דבר משנה, dvar mishnah, then it wasn't even a
good ruling to begin with. It was obviously wrong, and that's when
it can be overridden. If it's a mistake in שיקול הדעת, shikul
hadaat, that's when the first ruling also had legitimacy and it cannot
be overridden. All right, so let's take a look. כאן שטעה בשיקול
הדעת. kan shetaah beshikul hadaat. דאמר רב ששת אמר רב אסי טעה
בדבר משנה חוזר טעה בשיקול הדעת אינו חוזר. da'amar Rav Sheshet amar
Rav Assi ta'ah bidvar mishnah chozer ta'ah beshikul hadaat eino chozer. Okay,
so no longer it's a difference of a מומחה mumche or not
a מומחה. mumche. When it's just
in—when it's an issue of שיקול הדעת, shikul hadaat, of judgment call
but it wasn't blatantly wrong, then the ruling is binding, and whether
you're liable or not to the party that you're now saying that
you wronged depends on whether you're a מומחה mumche or not a
מומחה. mumche. But because the first ruling had legitimacy, even if now
you want to go the other way, but if it was just
an issue of judgment, then the first ruling remains binding. If it
was completely off
Now, what do you mean by דבר משנה? dvar mishnah? Do you
literally mean the משנה? mishnah? What about if you make a mistake
in something that's taught in a תוספתא? tosefta? You know, that's רב
חייא Rav Chiya and רב אושעיא. Rav Oshaya. אמר ליה: Amar lay:
In, yes. If it's clear ruling, then that is then it's a
black-letter law, then that's then that's not a legitimate ruling and is
overridden. אפילו הכי, Afilu hachi, אמר ליה: amar lay: In, אפילו בדבר
רב ושמואל. afilu bidvar Rav u'Shmuel.
What about if it's post-משנה? mishnah? Do you know, how literally do
you mean משנה? mishnah? What about if it's a ruling of the
אמוראים? Amoraim? אמר ליה: Amar lay: In, he said to him, yes.
So אפילו בדידי ובדידך, afilu bdidi u'vdidach,
how about us, רבינא Ravina and רב אשי, Rav Ashi, the last
generation of the אמוראים? Amoraim? If somebody got something we said, you
know, it was a clearly accepted ruling and got it wrong, would
that also be, you know, טועה בדבר משנה? to'eh bdvar mishnah? אמר
ליה: Amar lay: אטו אנן כקיצי דקני באגמא נן? Atu, anan k'kitzay
d'kanay b'agma nan? What are we, chop liver? Literally means, what are
we, are we like cutting reeds in the swamp? You know, our
rulings also have great weight. So, okay, so then what's a שיקול
הדעת shikul hadaat mistake? So היכי דמי שיקול הדעת? heichi dami shikul
hadaat? What do you mean by שיקול הדעת? shikul hadaat? אמר רב
פפא: Amar Rav Papa: כגון תרי תנאי או תרי אמוראי דפליגי אהדדי.
k'gon tray tannay o tray amoray d'pligi ahadadi. What, you know, that
black-letter law is not just some תנא tanna said it or some
אמורא amora said it, because as we know, the גמרא Gemara and
the משנה mishnah is filled with debates. So when we said now
that it's דבר משנה, dvar mishnah, it means it was said by
a תנא, tanna, it was said by an אמורא, amora, and that
was the accepted פסק. psak. Okay, and if somebody is ignoring something
in the, you know, in the גמרא, Gemara, in the משנה, mishnah,
the גמרא Gemara that's accepted פסק, psak, then they're totally off base.
It's a, not a legitimate פסק psak to begin with. What's a
error, but it's a שיקול הדעת shikul hadaat error? That there's a
debate in the גמרא. Gemara. It's not clear what the הלכה halacha
is. כגון תרי תנאי או תרי אמוראי דפליגי אהדדי. k'gon tray tannay
o tray amoray d'pligi ahadadi. So either תנאים tannaim disagree or אמוראים
Amoraim disagree. ולא איתמר הלכתא לא כמר ולא כמר, v'lo itmar hilchata
lo k'mar v'lo k'mar, and the it was not declared black and
white how we פסקן. pasken.
ואקרי ועבד כחד מינייהו, v'ikri v'avid k'chad minayhu, and it happened that
he decided he was going to side with one opinion.
וסוגיא דשמעתא, v'sugya d'shma'ta, some say סוגיא דעלמא, sugya d'alma, אזלי כאידך,
azli k'idach, but the general accepted approach of the, of the הלכה,
halacha, even though it's not absolutely ruled, like you know, there's a
lot of things that are debated but there's a weight of the
פוסקים poskim is in one direction. Okay, so the weight goes in
that direction. היינו שיקול הדעת. hainu shikul hadaat. That's a mistake in
judgment. Now again, this a lot of this is left unclear. I
mean, why is it a mistake in judgment? If he considered the
debate and he sided with the minority, you know, why is it
an error? Like that's the opinion that appeared correct to him and
he's entitled to rule like that as long as it's not פסקן
pasken one way. So maybe that's the point. Maybe that's why it's
מעשה עשוי, ma'aseh asui, because his original ruling was legitimate, but now
it also can constitute a טעות ta'ut because now he's changed his
mind and he's now persuaded by the majority opinion, or you know,
by where the general consensus lies. So that type of a case,
we recognize that because now you're siding with that, if you had
stuck to your guns, it would have been legitimate, end of story.
Nobody would have made you pay. Nobody could come along and say,
"Oh, but more פוסקים poskim go the other way so you made
a mistake." But if you yourself basically, you know, sort of concede
that you, that you should have ruled like the majority, okay, then
you're saying you made a mistake in judgment and it really is
a mistake because, you know, more of the weight is with the
opinion that you're siding with now. That seems to be the explanation
here. But if you went against what was accepted פסק, psak, then
it wasn't even פסק psak to begin with and you reverse it.
So that makes a lot of sense conceptually. Now there's a very
interesting, you know, debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about how far does
this go. Like the גמרא Gemara went up through the time of
the אמוראים. Amoraim. Does it continue up to the rulings of the
גאונים? Geonim? If the גאונים Geonim there's a consensus about and you,
and you פסקן pasken otherwise, you know, is that שיקול הדעת shikul
hadaat or is that דבר משנה? dvar mishnah? And that's really a
very important discussion in the whole issue about, you know, the authority.
What gets canonized? We know that as a matter of like the
way הלכה halacha operates, if you say something that is contradicted absolutely
by the גמרא, Gemara, then that's clearly a mistake in ruling. That's
טועה בדבר משנה. to'eh bdvar mishnah. Okay, you, nothing you can say,
you know, can be in contradiction to what is the clear position
of the גמרא. Gemara. What about, so that's like effectively a type
of canonizing of the halachic authority of the גמרא, Gemara, right? What
if you say something that goes against what all of the גאונים
Geonim say, however? So that is a question of: Do the גאונים
Geonim get that canonized type of work? And then later it becomes
a question of: How about what all the ראשונים Rishonim say, and
so on? And there's different opinions in the ראשונים Rishonim about the
authority of the גאונים. Geonim.
And some... make a distinction between if you were not aware of
what they said and once you became aware you realized that you
were persuaded by it, right, that's like one thing. That could be
like a טועה בדבר משנה Toeh b'dvar Mishna because you were just
ignorant of relevant information. But if you knew what they said and
you פסקת paskened otherwise, then that's your prerogative, you know, the same
way in the גמרא, Gemara, if an אמורא Amora knew what an
אמורא Amora said and a different אמורא Amora פסק paskened otherwise, that
was their prerogative. So really interesting questions here about authority and canonization.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues and says like this: איתיבי
רב המנונא לרב ששת. Aiteivi Rav Hamnuna l'Rav Sheshet. So רב המנונא
Rav Hamnuna challenged רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, this idea about when we
think that דיני ממונות dinei mamonot can be חוזר. chozer. Okay, מעשה
בפרה שנטלה אם שלה, Maaseh b'parah she-nitlah em shelah, there's a story
of a פרה, parah, some say שובט מנחם, Shovet Menachem, that the
uterus had been removed. והאכילה רבי טרפון לכלבים, Ve-he-achilah Rabbi Tarfon l'klavim,
and Rabbi Tarfon said it's a טרפה. treifah. They slaughtered it, they
found that the uterus had been removed, or maybe they knew they
had removed the uterus in an operation during life, and then they
slaughtered it, and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said it can't survive, it's
a טרפה. treifah. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים ביבנה, U-va maaseh lifnei Chachamim
be-Yavneh, and this came before the sages in Yavneh, והתירוה, ve-hitirua, and
they permitted it, שאמר תודוס הרופא, she-amar Todos ha-Rofeh, because Todos the
doctor said, אין פרה וחזירה יוצאת מאלכסנדריא של מצרים, ein parah ve-chazirah
yotzet me-Alexandria shel Mitzrayim, no cow or
sow, female pig, will go out from Alexandrian Egypt, אלא אם כן
חותכין האם שלה. ela im ken chotchin ha-em shelah. They want to
preserve, you know,
this is their you know their export product here is their you
know the cows and the pigs, or maybe the meat from them,
and they don't want people to raise them outside of Alexandria, so
they if they're going to sell a cow or pig outside of
Alexandria, you know they don't want to give away the technology as
it would be, they're going to cut out the uterus so people
cannot raise them outside. Okay, and כדי שלא תלד, kedei she-lo teled,
so it shouldn't give birth. And of course the animal survived. So
it is possible not to have a uterus and to survive. So
אמר רבי טרפון, amar Rabbi Tarfon, so רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon clearly
made a mistake, and by the way, it's a משנה Mishna now.
Was the משנה Mishna written in the time of רבי טרפון? Rabbi
Tarfon? Is an interesting question. But anyway, the משנה Mishna says that
an animal missing its uterus is not a טרפה. treifah. So this
was considered like to be obvious information, whether it had been written
as a משנה Mishna or not, that was available, that he was
not aware of, that he had made a mistake about. So that
was a טועה בדבר משנה. Toeh b'dvar Mishna. ואמר רבי טרפון, ve-amar
Rabbi Tarfon, הא חכא חמור טרפון. hacha chamor Tarfon. Oy, you've gone
and fell your donkey Rabbi Tarfon to pay for the you know
this guy back
for his cow that you טרפה treifed up. All right, now that
has to do with a question about whether you're חייב, chayav, presumably
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon was a מומחה, mumcheh, why does he have
civil liability? But the גמרא Gemara first wants to understand about whether
it gets reversed or not. So let's take a look. So אמר
לו רבי עקיבא, amar lo Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said
to him, פטור אתה, patur atah, no don't worry רבי טרפון, Rabbi
Tarfon, you're exempt, שכל המומחה לרבים פטור מלשלם. she-kol ha-mumcheh l'rabbim patur
milishalem. If you're an expert you're exempt. So that's what we talked
before, that an expert is exempt. Now, why is this a question
to what we've said? Let's take a look. ואי איתא, Ve-i ita,
the גמרא Gemara says if it's true, לימא ליה, leima lei, טועה
בדבר משנה אתה וטועה בדבר משנה חוזר. Toeh b'dvar Mishna atah ve-Toeh
b'dvar Mishna chozer. Why did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say to him,
oh don't worry you're exempt, why he should have said to him,
wait you made a mistake with a דבר משנה, dvar Mishna, so
the whole ruling reverses itself, so there's no liability to begin with.
Now obviously you're thinking that doesn't make sense, you can't reverse it
here because the animal has already been fed to the dogs. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara is going to ask that. It doesn't really
make sense what the question is, we'll see how the גמרא Gemara
explains it. But ignoring right now that it was fed to the
dogs, why did he say you're exempt because you're a מומחה? mumcheh?
He should have said it was טועה בדבר משנה Toeh b'dvar Mishna
and that's חוזר. chozer.
חדא ועוד קאמר, Chada ve-od ka-amar, he was saying one plus another
thing. חדא, Chada, דטועה בדבר משנה אתה. de-Toeh b'dvar Mishna atah. Number
one is you made a mistake regarding a clear ruling and therefore
it's not even a ruling at all. Okay, וטועה בדבר משנה חוזר,
ve-Toeh b'dvar Mishna chozer, and therefore it's reversed. ועוד, Ve-od, and in
addition, אינמי בשיקול הדעת טעית, inami be-shikul ha-daat ta'ita, even if your
mistake was a judgment call mistake, okay, and
your original ruling would be standing, מומחה לרבים אתה, mumcheh l'rabbim atah,
you're still an expert and accepted expert, וכל המומחה לרבים פטור מלשלם,
ve-chol ha-mumcheh l'rabbim patur milishalem, and therefore you're exempt from paying. All
right, so fine, so we understand all of that, he's a מומחה,
mumcheh, he's exempt, but the only thing we really don't understand is
why the גמרא Gemara thought it was a question. Whether טועה בדבר
משנה Toeh b'dvar Mishna is חוזר chozer or אינו חוזר, eino chozer,
it was too late for anything to reverse itself here, the animal
had already been fed to the dogs. So let's take a look.
So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
le-Rava, מאי קמותיב רב המנונא לרב ששת מפרה? mai ka-moteiv Rav Hamnuna
le-Rav Sheshet mi-parah? I don't understand the question that was being asked
here from the case of this cow. פרה הרי האכילה לכלבים וליתא
דתהדר. Parah harei he-achilah l'klavim ve-leita de-tehadar. It's been fed to the
dogs, it can't reverse. Oh look you see, even though it was
a טועה בדבר משנה Toeh b'dvar Mishna you can't reverse it. No,
he couldn't reverse it because it was fed to the dogs.
הכי קאמר ליה, Hachi ka-amar lei, here was the question. אי אמרת
בשלמא טועה בדבר משנה אינו חוזר, Ei amart bishlama Toeh b'dvar Mishna
eino chozer, if you think normally that טועה בדבר משנה Toeh b'dvar
Mishna even that you can't reverse it, אלמא קם דינא, alman kam
dina, so then as soon as you ruled the ruling was binding.
So היינו דקמפחיד hainu dekamfachid רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon וקאמר ליה veka'amar
leih אי אומן לגבייהו דאת ואת פטור מלשלם. ei oman legabeihu de'at
ve'at patur milishalem. So רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon was afraid, my ruling
made this irreversibly טריפה treifa and now and he was afraid that
I'm going to be liable. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to
him: No, you're a מומחה, mumche, you're not liable. Okay. אלא אי
אמרת טעות בדבר משנה חוזר, ela ei amart ta'ut bidvar Mishna chozer,
but if we were to rule that a טעות בדבר משנה ta'ut
bidvar Mishna is חוזר, chozer, which is how we do rule, לימא
ליה, leima leih, so even though it's true that the owner, now
it sounds a little bit like רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon actively fed
it to the dogs, but the גמרא Gemara here is going to
assume that רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon ruled that it was טריפה treifa
and the owner fed it to the dogs. So what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is, if טעות בדבר משנה ta'ut bidvar Mishna is
חוזר, chozer, then לימא ליה leima leih כיון דאילו הוי פרה דינא
לאו דינא ולאו כלום ולאו כלום עבדת השתא נמי לאו כלום עבדת.
keivan de'ilu havei para dina lav dina velav klum velav klum avadat
hashta nami lav klum avadat. So why didn't רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
say to him: Look, had they not fed the dogs the cow
to the dogs, your ruling would not have been binding. It was
a טעות בדבר משנה. ta'ut bidvar Mishna. And therefore the force of
your ruling itself had no binding nature. And since that would have
been true if the cow was around, and it would have been
reversed, and the cow wouldn't be a טריפה, treifa, so that shows
that your ruling was not binding. Since your ruling was not binding,
so even though the owner went and fed it to the dogs,
it wasn't your ruling that did it. It was his feeding to
the dogs. Okay. So the question was: If טעות בדבר משנה ta'ut
bidvar Mishna is חוזר chozer and it's not a ruling, why did
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva just say to him: You're exempt because you're
a מומחה? mumche? He should have said: You're exempt because your ruling
by itself didn't do anything. The owner then decided to feed it
to the dogs. Now, it was decided because he thought your ruling
was binding, but that has to do with issues of indirect and
גרמא grama and so on. In as far as your ruling wasn't
binding in itself, you're not liable for the owner then deciding to
feed it to the dogs. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: You're
right. He could have said that. It was a טעות בדבר משנה,
ta'ut bidvar Mishna, your ruling itself really didn't mean anything, okay, and
you have no liability of how the owner acted afterwards. And you're
also not liable because you're a מומחה לרבים. mumche lerabbim. Fine. Anyway,
what we see here is we now have one answer that מומחה
לרבים mumche lerabbim can be חוזר chozer when he's backed by a
higher authority. And we have another answer, very satisfying answer, that forget
מומחה mumche or not מומחה, mumche, that's only a difference about liability,
but the real issue here is whether you are, what type of
a mistake it was. A judgment call mistake, the original ruling was
legitimate and binding, now that you're saying you made a judgment call
you could have liability, okay, there's a degree of mistake. But if
it's a טעות בדבר משנה, ta'ut bidvar Mishna, it was never binding
at all and it is totally reversed. All right. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. רב חסדא אמר כאן שנטל ונתן ביד
כאן שלא נטל ונתן ביד. Rav Chisda amar kan shenatal venatan beyad
kan shelo natal venatan beyad. He says there's a distinction between whether
you physically handed it over, like you say, ראובן Reuven you're חייב
chayav a hundred dollars and you take the hundred dollars out of
ראובן's Reuven hand and you hand it to שמעון, Shimon, or whether
you just give your ruling and you don't say anything. Now, that
distinction could have been a difference about whether there's liability, right? The
degree that if you physically caused the damage, you're liable, if you
just did it verbally you're not. But that's not the point the
גמרא Gemara is making. The גמרא Gemara is saying that's the difference
between whether it's חוזר chozer or לא חוזר. lo chozer. When you
do something to act, to demonstrate the fact that like this is
how you're ruling, that gives it some finality that you can't be
חוזר. chozer. I don't really fully understand why, maybe it's a question
of זילותא דבי דינא, ziluta debei dina, okay, but that makes it
official and final because you've acted on it. Even though, even though
you could just reverse it and have the guy give the money
back, that finalizes it. And when we talked before about liability and
you can't reverse it, that is, I'm sorry, when you talked before
about you can't reverse it, that's when you physically handed it over.
When our משנה Mishna says that it can be reversed, that's when
it was just your words and then you can reverse. All right,
that's an interesting distinction, not totally understandable what the conceptually is behind
that, but fine.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלמא חייב את הזכאי.
bishlama chiyav et hazakkai. Okay, so now the cases are therefore in
the that we quoted here, not in the משנה Mishna but the
other תוספתא Tosefta that we source we quoted, that said that it
was that the liability of
when you give the ruling and that you can't reverse. So now
we're saying that that was all when it was actually what do
you call it, it was actually a
נטל ונתן ביד. natal venatan beyad. So let's say how, let's see
how that plays out in all those cases. בשלמא חייב את הזכאי,
bishlama chiyav et hazakkai, when you made the person who was innocent
and you ruled him to be liable, משכחת לה שנטל ונתן ביד,
mashkachat lah shenatal venatan beyad, you took the hundred dollars out of
ראובן's Reuven hand and you handed it to שמעון Shimon and you
said you owe him a hundred dollars.
And therefore you made a mistake and now you're liable. אלא זיכה
את החייב, ela zikkah et hachayyav, but when you said that somebody
who is liable was exempt, you said, ראובן, Reuven, you're exempt, you
don't owe שמעון Shimon anything, but he really did owe him a
hundred dollars. Okay. So היכי משכחת לה? heichi meshkachat lah? And then
it said that you're now
the ruling is
ruled. So how is that a case when it can't be reversed
of נתו ונסב ביד? naso v'nasav biyod? You just said you're exempt,
there was nothing to hand over. You just said ראובן Reuven you
don't have to pay שמעון. Shimon. So how is that a נתו
ונסב ביד? naso v'nasav biyod? היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachas lah? דאמר
ליה פטור אתה. d'amar lei patur ata. So you just said ראובן
Reuven you're exempt. והלו נתו ונסב ביד? v'halo naso v'nasav biyod? But
you didn't hand anything over, you just exempted ראובן. Reuven. The גמרא
Gemara says כיון דאמר פטור אתה כמאן דנתו ונסב ביד דמי. keivan
d'amar patur ata k'man d'naso v'nasav biyod dami.
Since you said you're exempt and then everybody walked home and there
was nothing left to be done, that's like נתו ונסב ביד. naso
v'nasav biyod. So you see here that the נתו ונסב ביד naso
v'nasav biyod which makes it not able to be reversed really just
means it reached a certain finality. There was nothing left to be
done. Once it's fully over, then it can't be reversed. If you
say you're exempt, it's fully over. If you say that you're חייב,
chayav, it's only over if you actually the money is handed over.
But still, it has to be you who's doing the one handing
it over. You finalized it, you did that last thing to make
it over, that's when it can no longer be reversed.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay, אלא מתניתין דקתני דיני ממונות מחזירין
בין לזכות בין לחובה. ela masnisin d'katni dinei mamonos machzirin bein l'zchus
bein l'chova. Okay, but now that's fine. That's the case when it's
נתו ונסב ביד. naso v'nasav biyod. פטור אתה patur ata constitutes that,
and that's the case of the teaching we had at the beginning
of the דף daf that you have to pay, you might have
to pay if you're not a מומחה. mumcha. Our משנה mishna that
says you can reverse it is a case where לא נתו ונסב
ביד. lo naso v'nasav biyod. Let's see what that scenario is. אלא
מתניתין דקתני דיני ממונות מחזירין בין לזכות בין לחובה, ela masnisin d'katni
dinei mamonos machzirin bein l'zchus bein l'chova, that you reverse it whether
to find the person innocent or liable, exempt or liable. בשלמא לזכות
משכחת לה דאמר ליה מעיקרא חייב אתה ולא נתו ונסב ביד. bishlama
l'zchus mashkachas lah d'amar lei mei'ikara chayav ata v'lo naso v'nasav biyod.
So I get how you can now find him free from liability.
That's first you said you owe a hundred dollars, you did not
take it out of his hand and hand it over, and now
you call back and say you're exempt. So because there was לא
נתו ונסב ביד, lo naso v'nasav biyod, since you didn't hand the
money over, now you can get now you can reverse it and
say ראובן Reuven you're exempt. אלא לחובה היכי משכחת לה? ela l'chova
heichi mashkachas lah? But what's the reverse case? First you said ראובן
Reuven you're exempt, and now you're going to reverse it and say
ראובן Reuven you're חייב. chayav. דאמר ליה מעיקרא פטור אתה. d'amar lei
mei'ikara patur ata.
First you said ראובן Reuven you're exempt. So then how can now
you reverse it and say you're חייב? chayav? והאמרת כיון דאמר ליה
פטור אתה כמאן דנתו ונסב ביד דמי? v'amart keivan d'amar lei patur
ata k'man d'naso v'nasav biyod dami? But you just said that as
soon as you said you're exempt and it's done, that's like you
handed it over. Now you can't reverse it. Okay, so we had
the case where it can't be reversed when you're saying you're פטור,
patur, and we said oh, when you say you're פטור, patur, that's
like נתו ונסב ביד naso v'nasav biyod and you can't reverse it.
So what's the case in our משנה mishna when you said you're
פטור patur and you can reverse it if it's like נתו ונסב
ביד? naso v'nasav biyod? So the גמרא Gemara says you know what?
חדא קתני. chada katni. Really our משנה mishna is not two cases,
it's one case. דיני ממונות מחזירין לזכות שהיא חובה. dinei mamonos machzirin
l'zchus shehi chova. When it says what happened was it's only one
case in our משנה. mishna. He said ראובן Reuven you're חייב. chayav.
That
was making ראובן Reuven חייב chayav and finding against ראובן Reuven and
in favor of שמעון. Shimon. And you weren't נתו ונסב ביד. naso
v'nasav biyod. Now you're going to call the case back and you're
going to say ראובן Reuven you're exempt. So in that one ruling
of ראובן Reuven you're exempt, which you can do because there was
no נתו ונסב ביד, naso v'nasav biyod, you've now made the חייב
chayav one, ראובן, Reuven, פטור, patur, and you've now made the פטור
patur one or the one you found in favor with, שמעון, Shimon,
חייב. chayav. You've now hurt him. Okay, so it's really one case.
You found ראובן Reuven innocent which actually made the other person the
one who lost. It's not two separate cases. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, that doesn't work because the גמרא Gemara says דכוותיה גבי
נפשות מחזירין לזכות ואין מחזירין לחובה. d'chvosei gabei nefashos machzirin l'zchus v'ein
machzirin l'chova.
Now we're going to have to say that the parallel ruling that
by ממונות mamonos you can reverse call back for either way, but
you really mean one case where one person is benefited and one
person is hurt, and then it contrasts it to a capital case
where it says you can call him back to find him innocent
but not to find him guilty. So how could we be talking
about one case that has both elements there? מחזירין לזכות ואין מחזירין
לחובה. machzirin l'zchus v'ein machzirin l'chova. מחזירין לזכות זכות גרידתא. machzirin l'zchus
zchus geridasa.
Finding him innocent is just fine. Just one person. You said you're
חייב מיתה chayav misa because you were מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos and
now you say you're innocent. Okay. ואין מחזירין לחובה. v'ein machzirin l'chova.
But you can't reverse call back if there's liability. So now parallel
to the דיני ממונות dinei mamonos case we're going to say it's
one case that's going to make one person innocent and one person
liable. Well, what's that case? זכות שהיא חובה חובתיה דמאן? zchus shehi
chova chovasei d'man?
When will there ever be a case that you'll find the guy
innocent that you're hurting some other person? So the גמרא Gemara says
הא לא קשיא. ha lo kashya. No, I can come up with
a case. חובתיה דגואל הדם. chovasei d'goel hadam.
You said ראובן Reuven you committed murder which was a חובה chova
to ראובן, Reuven, and now you're going to call him back and
find him innocent but it's going to say ah, you can't do
that because so משום חובתי דגואל הדם קטלינן ליה להאי
mishum chovasi degoel hadam
katlinan lei lehai because we don't want שמעון Shimon the גואל הדם
goel hadam to be hurt by this ruling we're going to not
bring ראובן's Reuven's case back and find him innocent? so משום חובתי
דגואל הדם קטלינן ליה להאי mishum chovasi degoel hadam katlinan lei lehai
because we don't want שמעון Shimon the גואל הדם goel hadam to
be hurt by this ruling we're going to not bring ראובן's Reuven's
case back and find him innocent? That goes against everything we know.
ועוד מאי בין בין veod mai bein bein and says you reverse
whether for his זכות zechus or whether for חובה. chova. So it's
clear we're talking about two separate cases. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says קשיא, kashya, you're right, when you get to דיני נפשות dinei
nefashos we are talking about two separate cases and you can bring
and you bring back only to find him innocent not to find
him guilty. But still in the דיני ממונות dinei mammonos case
we're talking about one case which reverses who is innocent and who
is guilty. That's at least the גמרא's Gemara's claim. But that's because
we're trying to say that the only cases you can reverse are
those that are לא נטל ונתן ביד. lo natol venasan beyad. And
we have to sort of but we were forced to say that
when you say פטור pattur it is like נטל ונתן ביד natol
venasan beyad so we can't really figure out what's the case of
פטור pattur that you can reverse once we've declared that to be
like נטל ונתן ביד. natol venasan beyad. So רבינא אמר. Ravina amar.
So רבינא Ravina has a better way of explaining what is the
נטל ונתן ביד natol venasan beyad in a case of פטור. pattur.
רבינא אמר כגון דהוה ליה משכון ונטלו הימנו. Ravina amar kegon dehava
lei mashkon unetalo heimenu. So רבינא Ravina says no no no here's
how it's worked. Okay,
ראובן Reuven said you know שמעון Shimon owes me a hundred dollars
and you said שמעון Shimon you're exempt so that was saying his
פטור. pattur. How is it נטל ונתן ביד? natol venasan beyad? Because
now what you did is you took שמעון's Shimon's collateral away from
ראובן Reuven and gave it back to שמעון. Shimon. So now that
makes it nice and simple. Okay, when can you reverse it? When
it's לא נטל ונתן ביד. lo natol venasan beyad. When can you
not reverse it? When it is נטל ונתן ביד. natol venasan beyad.
What is a case of נטל ונתן ביד natol venasan beyad when
you say שמעון Shimon you're exempt? It's not just those words because
then you'd have that also is a case of when you're able
to reverse it. So no, it's when you actually take the collateral
out of ראובן's Reuven's hand and hand it to שמעון. Shimon. That
makes that case not reversible. טימאת את הטהור. timas es hatahor. Now
what's a case we're just going to finish this up that you
made something that was טהור tahor טמא tamei that you did it
ביד beyad so it can't be reversed? דאדי ביה שרץ. daadi bei
sheretz. You said you wanted to prove your point that says that
this תרומה terumah is טהור tahor is טמא tamei and just to
prove my point I'm going to take a שרץ sheretz like this
bug and I'm going to throw it on it you know or
this rodent or whatever to show you that I am confident that
it is טמא. tamei. And you did it בידיים beyadayim and now
it can't be reversed. טיהרת את הטמא. tihartas es hatamei. How do
you actually actively physically show something that you said was טמא tamei
you said it was טהור tahor and how what would be a
case that you did it בידיים beyadayim that it can't be reversed?
How do you make something טהור tahor בידיים? beyadayim? שעירבן בפירותיו. sheiravan
befirotav. You mixed up this something this thing that was suspected of
being טמא tamei you mixed it up with the guy's other produce
to show and demonstrate how confident you were that it was טהור.
tahor. Okay, so that's a more satisfying answer of רבינא Ravina not
to make words like it's נטל ונתן ביד natol venasan beyad that
gets us all caught up because we need to keep those cases
separate. So again let's just review. What are the three answers of
how it can be reversed in דיני ממונות? dinei mammonos? One is
with a מומחה mumcheh but that there's a somebody even higher than
him that backs it up that makes the second decision more legitimate.
The second very satisfying and very important in terms of canonization issues
is when it's a judgment call it can't be reversed and that's
when there's liability unless you're מומחה mumcheh then you're free from liability.
But when it's against black letter law totally accepted פסק psak משנה
Mishnah גמרא Gemara whatever and so on then it was clearly not
even a ruling to begin with and then it can be reversed.
And the last answer is that you know even within presumably the
cases of presumably it doesn't argue on the second answer but presumably
even within the cases of שיקול הדעת shikul hadaas if you acted
on it and physically נטל ונתן ביד natol venasan beyad to demonstrate
your ruling then it is then you can't reverse it even after
even if you've made you know made a mistake but if it's
but if it wasn't נטל ונתן ביד natol venasan beyad it could
be reversed. Presumably that's within the categories of שיקול הדעת. shikul hadaas.
Once it's דבר משנה devar Mishnah presumably that always is automatically off
base and reversible. Okay, let's just do one more section.
דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos.
This is now the other side of this. When it comes to
capital cases you can always call back to find the guy innocent
but no double jeopardy. מנין ליוצא מבית דין חייב ואמר אחד יש
לי ללמד עליו זכות? minayin leyotze mibeis din chayav veamar echad yesh
li lelamed alav zechus? How do you know if somebody was ruled
already that he is liable to be put to death and somebody
says oh wait I can now have a new reason to find
him innocent? מנין שמחזירין אותו? minayin shemachzirin oso? How do you know
you'll call the case back and review it and possibly reverse it?
תלמוד לומר talmud lomar נקי אל תהרוג naki al taharog it says
ונקי וצדיק אל תהרוג. venaki vetzadik al taharog. ונקי וצדיק אל תהרוג.
venaki vetzadik al taharog. Don't kill the innocent and the righteous. Now
the difference is נקי naki means genuinely innocent regardless of how the
case was ruled. צדיק tzadik means צדיק בדינו, tzadik bedino, somebody who
the ruling went in his favor, right? So it's like, you know,
normally they talk about finding somebody guilty or not guilty. The court
doesn't find the person innocent. All right, but here, so what we're
saying is נקי אל תהרוג naki al taharog means even if this
person was found רשע, rasha, was ruled against that he had done
it, he might still be innocent. We might have made a mistake.
So in order to make sure that we're not killing an innocent
person, we will call the case back. נקי אל תהרוג. naki al
taharog. מניין ליוצא מבית דין זכאי ואמר אחד יש לי ללמד עליו
חובה מניין שאין מחזירין אותו? Minayin leyotzei mibeit din zakai veamar echad
yesh li lelamed alav chovah minayin sheein machzirin oto? How do you
know that if somebody was
ruled that they were innocent, meaning the case was ruled in their
favor, how do you know you don't bring the person back if
now there might be a basis to say that they were guilty?
תלמוד לומר צדיק אל תהרוג. Talmud lomar tzadik al taharog. Don't kill
somebody who is found righteous in his judgment. So if the judgment
was passed in his favor and he was a צדיק, tzadik, no
double jeopardy. You do not reopen the possibility that he might be
guilty. He is off. You will not kill him. And if the
person might be innocent, even if he was found guilty, even if
he's a possibly a נקי, naki, you will revisit the case. Okay.
אמר רב שימי
בר אשי וחילופא למסית. Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi vechilufa lemeisit. The
reverse is about a seducer to idolatry. That person you will bring
it back to find him חייב, chayav, you won't bring him back
to find him innocent. דכתיב לא תחמול ולא תכסה עליו. dechtiv lo
tachmol velo techaseh alav. Do not have any compassion on him. We
had something similar about טוענין למסית. toanim lemeisit. רב כהנא מתני כי
הרוג תהרגנו, Rav Kahana matni ki harog tahragenu, you shall surely kill
him. So by a מסית, meisit, somebody enticing to idolatry, we try
to find all reasons to find him חייב, chayav, but somebody for
any other thing, we try to find anything that will find him
innocent. Or once ruled that he is innocent, we will not try
to do anything, he will, you know, no double jeopardy. בעי מיניה
רב זירא מרב ששת. Ba'ei minei Rav Zeira meRav Sheshet. Rav Zeira
asked Rav Sheshet: חייבי גלויות מניין, Chayei galuyos minayin, or מאי? mai?
How do you know or does this apply, this idea that you
know, no double jeopardy, we don't bring you back, you know, even
to somebody who is
חייב chayav not for what's in the דיני נפשות dinei nefashot category?
Let's say it's not capital, but let's say it's sending somebody into
exile. So he said yeah, you're also, we also will bring you
back, you know, we'll only bring you back for זכות zechut not
for חובה. chovah. אתיא רוצח רוצח. Atia rotzeach rotzeach. It says murderer
by both cases of the גואל הדם goel hadam and an intentional
murderer. So the same way we don't kill a whatever, you know,
we don't bring back a case for a murderer, we won't bring
back a case for a case of חייב גלות. chayav galut. חייבי
מלקיות מניין? Chayei malkuyos minayin? How do you know by somebody's חייב
מלקות chayav malkot or what's the הלכה? halacha? אתיא רשע רשע. Atia
rasha rasha. It says אשר הוא רשע למות asher hu rasha lamut
in both places. So we make a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. So
both, all those cases basically the ruling is we will call the
case back after the גמר דין gmar din to possibly find the
person innocent, but once the person has been ruled and has been
found innocent in the court, we will never call it back to
now possibly find him guilty, no double jeopardy. תניא נמי הכי. Tanya
nami hachi. We taught similarly: חייבי גלויות מניין אתיא רוצח רוצח חייבי
מלקיות מניין אתיא רשע רשע. Chayei galuyos minayin atia rotzeach rotzeach chayei
malkuyos minayin atia rasha rasha. I should point out though that this
is again goes to this issue that the משנה mishna sets up
this difference of civil and capital, but there are a lot of
cases in the middle. So מלקות malkus and גלות galus and you
know, all those cases where you're basically found wicked as it were
and deserving of punishment and it's a crime, it's not civil, those
are being put
in the דיני נפשות dinei nefashot category for this idea that no
double jeopardy. However, you know, it's clearly not in other parts of
the משנה mishna because מלקות malkus is a בית דין beit din
of three and nevertheless and the משנה mishna made the difference between
three and twenty-three. So the משנה mishna is not exactly consistent always
which is in the דיני ממונות dinei mammonot category and which is
in the דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, but for this הלכה halacha about
double jeopardy, you know, מלקות malkus and גלות galus is in the
דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. What about the case about פותחין לזכות פותחין
לחובה? posin le-zchus possin le-chovah? Those types of questions also not clear
in the משנה. mishna. All right, to be continued.